Physicians spend 12 hours per week
on prior authorizations.
That's 43 requests per physician,
costing the healthcare system
31 billion dollars annually.
The problem? Clinical data is locked
in fragmented EHR systems,
and payers require extensive documentation
in formats physicians don't have time to prepare.
AuthClear solves this with two AI agents:
a FHIR terminology engine
and a prior authorization copilot.
Let me show you how it works.
AuthClear consists of two agents.
First, the MCP Server:
a clinical terminology engine that translates
ICD-10, RxNorm, and LOINC codes
using FHIR R4 standards.
Second, the A2A Agent:
a prior authorization copilot that reads
patient data,
identifies requirements, and generates
structured authorization drafts.
Let's start with the MCP Server.
I'm resolving ICD-10 code E11.9 -
Type 2 Diabetes.
The server translates it to SNOMED code 44054006
and provides the clinical description.
Next, I look up the drug Ozempic.
The server returns the RxNorm ID,
drug class GLP-1 receptor agonist,
and confirms it requires prior authorization.
Finally, I retrieve the prior auth criteria
for semaglutide from a generic payer.
The server returns required diagnoses,
lab thresholds,
and medication trial requirements.
All of this happens in milliseconds
using hardcoded mappings for common codes,
with API fallback for rare cases.
The MCP Server is now ready
to serve the A2A Agent.
Now the A2A Agent.
I'm loading a synthetic FHIR bundle
for Maria González,
a 50-year-old patient with Type 2 Diabetes.
She has an HbA1c of 8.9%, BMI of 34,
and has tried Metformin and Glipizide
for over 3 months.
The agent parses the FHIR bundle,
extracts 1 diagnosis, 2 medications,
and 2 lab results.
It then calls the MCP Server to resolve
all clinical codes
and retrieve prior auth criteria for Ozempic.
Using Claude's reasoning, the agent analyzes
whether Maria meets the criteria:
HbA1c above 7.5? Yes.
BMI above 30? Yes.
Two oral agents tried? Yes.
All criteria met.
The agent generates a structured
prior authorization draft with 90% confidence,
clinical justification, and supporting evidence.
Most importantly, it flags this
for human review -
we never auto-approve.
AuthClear is compliant with state
AI transparency laws:
Texas SB 490, Arizona HB 2417,
and Maryland HB 1174.
Human-in-the-loop is architecturally enforced -
no agent can approve or deny authorizations.
The impact? For a 10-physician practice
processing 430 prior auths per week,
AuthClear saves 8 hours per week
in staff time.
That's $83,000 per year in labor costs alone.
AuthClear:
AI-powered prior authorization
that keeps physicians in control.